Finding Aid for Julius A. Clauss papers, 1908-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Julius A. Clauss papers 1908-1960
Clauss, Julius A., 1886-1973.
1 oversize folder
7 linear feet
85101 Aa 2; UAl
Steel industry engineer; vice-president in charge of engineering of Great Lakes Steel Corp., Ecorse, Michigan; chief of steel plant facilities for steel division, U. S. War Production Board, during World War II. Correspondence, writings, professional papers, and files relating to activities with the Association of Iron and Steel Engineers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the family of Julius Clauss (donor no. 5608 ) and came to the library in 1974-1975.
The collection is open to research.
Julius A. Clauss was born July 9, 1886 in Buffalo, New York. He left school at age 14 and found employment as a Western Union messenger, and then in a bakery. Eventually he became apprenticed to a machinist at Bethlehem Steel's Lackawanna plant.
Intrigued by his work, Clauss began to study mechanical engineering in 1901 by means of correspondence school. In 1908, he received a degree in mechanical engineering from the International Correspondence Schools. During 1907 he supplemented his correspondence course with studies in metallurgy at the Buffalo YMCA.
Having completed his formal education, Clauss worked for numerous steel companies in Buffalo, Youngstown and Cleveland gaining a wealth of practical experience by serving in positions of ever increasing importance. In 1926 he became the chief engineer of the Trumbull Steel Co. in Warren, Ohio. He was offered and accepted the position of chief engineer at the Great Lakes Steel Co. of Ecorse, Michigan in 1929. Clauss remained at Great Lakes Steel for the rest of his career. In 1944 he was made vice-president in charge of engineering, a post he retained until his retirement in 1952.
Clauss was appointed chief of steel plant facilities for the Steel Division of the War Production Board in October 1942. He was responsible for the production expansion program. In November 1943 he resigned his appointment.
In addition to his corporate responsibilities and governmental duties, Clauss was active in engineering societies and associations. He was particularly interested in the Association of Iron and Steel Engineers and helped organize its Detroit chapter. Through his work with engineering societies he became interested in the history of the steel making industry. Clauss actively read and wrote on this subject.
The Julius Clauss collection has been arranged into the following series: Personal / Biographical; Writings, Presentations and Background material; Organizational files; Photographs; and Motion Pictures. Although reflecting all phases of Clauss' career, the bulk of the collection relates to his work with Great Lakes Steel and his overall interest in the history of the steel industry.
Subjects:
Association of Iron and Steel Engineers.; Great Lakes Steel Corporation.; Engineers--Michigan.; Engineering.; Steel industry and trade--United States.; United States. War Production Board.; World War, 1939-1945.; Wyandotte (Mich.)--History.; Industries--Michigan--Ecorse.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Clauss, Julius A., 1886-1973.; Construction industry--Michigan--Ecorse.; Detroit (Mich.)--Streets.; Ecorse River (Mich.); Ecorse (Mich.); Eureka Iron Company.; Great Lakes Steel Corporation.; Interiors--Steel mills.; Laborers.; Railroads--Michigan.; River Rouge (Mich.); Shipping--Great Lakes.; Steel industry--Michigan--Ecorse.; Woodward Avenue (Detroit, Mich.); Wyandotte (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Personal / Biographical
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence undated, 1908-1952, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Various organizations (correspondence regarding) (Box 1)
  - Registration as engineer (correspondence regarding) (Box 1)
  - School material (correspondence regarding) (Box 1)
  - Patents, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Technical notes (Box 1)
- Writings, Presentations and Background material
  - "The Romance of Iron and Steel" (Box 1)
  - Data for "The Romance of Iron and Steel" (Box 1)
  - "The Steel Industry" (Box 1)
  - History of the steel industry (Box 1)
  - Production of First Bessemer steel in U.S. at Wyandotte, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Alloying (Box 1)
  - Blast Furnace air-conditioning Milling techniques (Box 1)
  - Open hearth furnaces (Box 1)
  - Oxygen in steel making Roll designing (Box 1)
  - Sponge Iron from Smith process (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous lectures and notes
    - 1925-1936 (Box 2)
    - 1938-1942 (Box 2)
    - 1942-1948 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles 1935-1937 (Box 2)
- Organizational files
  - Association of Iron and Steel Engineers (AISE)
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1935 (Box 2)
    - 1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937 (Box 2)
    - 1938 (Box 2)
    - 1939, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1940, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 2)
    - 1943 (Box 2)
    - 1944-1957 (Box 2)
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME) (Box 2)
  - War Production Board
    - 1943, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Steel Expansion Program, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Survey of Alloy and Forging Quality Carbon Steel (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Steel
    - Summary data (Box 2)
    - "The Development of the Great Lakes Steel Corp" 1936 (Box 3)
    - "New Coke and Blast Furnace Plant..." 1939 (Box 3)
    - "Description of the Great Lakes Steel Corp" 1942 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous historical material (Box 3)
    - Metallurgical school (Box 3)
    - Junior Executive Club (Box 3)
    - Safety program (Box 3)
    - Sponge iron (Box 3)
    - Reinforcing bars (Box 3)
    - Alterations 1927 (Box 3)
    - Piling report 1935-1936 (Box 3)
    - Power consumption 1937 (Box 3)
    - Gas distribution system 1937-1938 (Box 3)
    - Construction reports 1940 (Box 3)
    - Construction costs and estimates, Blast Furnace D 1950 (Box 3)
    - Construction of blast Furnace D 1950 (Box 3)
    - Litigation over extension of ore dock number 3 1960 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Technical data and reports
      - Blast furnaces (Box 3)
      - Hanna Furnace Division (Box 3)
      - Blast Furnace C (Box 3)
      - Buildings (Box 4)
      - Coke plant (Box 4)
      - Construction quantity and progress reports (Box 4)
      - Fuel oil (Box 4)
      - Foundations, piles and fill (Box 4)
      - Open hearth Furnace (Box 4)
      - Piling wood (Box 4)
      - Pollution (water) (Box 4)
      - Power (Box 4)
      - Power tests and reports from mills (Box 5)
      - Stockyard etc., 5 volumes (Box 5)
- Photographs
  (see also oversize folder UAl)
  - Personal
    - Family (Box 6)
    - JAC with others
      - Mill scenes (Box 6)
      - Office scenes, etc. (Box 6)
  - Eureka Iron Co./Wyandotte Rolling Mill Co. 1800s (Box 6)
  - Views of Detroit--Woodward Avenue (Box 6)
  - Great Lakes Steel Corporation
    - Aerial photographs (Box 6)
    - Construction/Operations
      - 1923 (Box 6)
      - 1929 (Box 6)
      - January-June 1930 (Box 6)
      - July-December 1930 (Box 6)
      - 1931-1933 (Box 6)
      - 1934-1935 (Box 6)
      - 1936 (Box 6)
      - January-June 1937 (Box 6)
      - July-September 1937 (Box 6)
      - October-December 1937 (Box 6)
      - 1938 (Box 6)
      - 1939-1942 (Box 6)
      - 1943-1946 (Box 6)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 6)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 6)
      - 1952-1954 (Box 6)
    - 3500 KW motor generator set, 1948 (Box 6)
  - "The Making of Iron"--hand colored prints of Great Lakes Steel operations, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Negatives
    - Great Lakes Steel, b&w (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes Steel, color (Box 6)
    - Personal (Box 6)
- Motion Pictures, all 16 mm, b&w, silent, except where noted
  - Construction
    - Trestle and new dock June 22, 1938 (Box 7)
      (film box 1)
    - New dock fill and forms July 22-25, 1938 (Box 7)
      (film box 2)
    - New coal dock and bins August 26, 1938 (Box 7)
      (film box 3)
    - Removing waste, Hanna Division (Box 7)
      (film can 1)
    - Driving steel test piles (Box 7)
      (film can 2)
    - Dismantling and rebuilding blast furnace "B" 1941 (Box 7)
      (open reel)
    - "Dismantling of boiler room equipment, rebuilding of 'C' furnace" (Box 7)
      (actually includes no dismantling scenes; also includes coal unloading scenes; some color sequences; open reel)
  - Steelmaking process, 2 film reels (in 1 can)
    (includes all parts of process, from unloading ore boats to steel rolls leaving plant on trucks, but sequences are not in order)
    - Reel 1
      - Ore sheds, unloading (Box 7)
        (color; formerly reel #3)
      - Steelmaking process (Box 7)
        (b&w; formerly reel #4)
      - Steelmaking process (Box 7)
        (b&w; formerly reel #5)
    - Reel 2
      - Steelmaking (Box 7)
        (color and b&w; formerly reel #6)
      - Final product -- sheet metal (Box 7)
        (color and b&w; formerly reel #7)